Hey in this episode we are gonna start
and adding it like so we download all
but we do have this div ID root so what
HTML so even though this looks like HTML
gonna delete this counter and I can add
again all we have to do is say import
now how can we create multiple of these
nothing's still happening here because
and again you can add any name you want
this is a random tweet I can just copy
reaction videos a react videos what a
great way to start now before we get
started I just want to let you know that
in this episode we're not gonna take a
look at all the advanced things and
crazy things we can do react I just want
to let you know and can explain how
everything works and how it's different
from vanilla JavaScript because the
mentality you need to write react code
is is way different from vanilla
JavaScript so prepare yourself get ready
and let's see what react is about all
right before we get started we actually
need to download nodejs so if you don't
have node installed you can go on no
chance org and you can download this
recommend it for most users ok you can
click here on download and after you do
that we can use NPM to install different
kinds of packages and what we're gonna
install is something called creates
react app and what create react app is
it's a package that kind of sets
everything up for us the whole
environment to start writing react code
without us doing any preparations ok so
just a very simple way for us to get
started and I highly recommend to use
this I mean I use it every time I rarely
set up my react projects from scratch so
we can go on google and write create
react app and we're gonna open up this
github page here so github.com slash
Facebook slash create react app and if
we scroll down here a bit we can have a
very simple way we can start our react
app and all we need to do is we need to
write npx create react app and then we
give it a name so let's open up vs code
add again stop talking so much and show
us what you mean alright so here I'm
just gonna I'm just gonna navigate we
can go to desktop I'm gonna go to open
folder actually I'm just gonna go to
desktop here okay and what we need to do
is we need to go to the terminal up here
and click on new terminal ok this is
gonna open up
our terminal as you can see I'm in the
projects folder here and all we need to
write this MPX create react app like so
we add a space and then we give it a
name and that's gonna create us D folder
with the react project so for now I'm
just gonna name this project react okay
hit enter so after we install everything
it's gonna say CD project reacts so what
CD means is basically we can navigate to
that specific folder so as you can see
down here it actually created the folder
with the react project for us so this is
just a basic template empty template
that we can start creating react
projects so we can do CD Projekt react
and that's gonna bring us into the
folder alright that's one way or you can
just open folder and that's what I'm
gonna do and I'm just gonna navigate
like so because I don't want you to see
all these different crazy projects going
on here so I'm just gonna navigate to it
like so and this already looks kind of
crazy so I'm gonna explain everything so
don't worry okay the first thing we have
here is no modules now what node modules
is is all the different packages that we
installed with NPM so if we take a look
here we're gonna have things like babel
react and react dom and all the other
crazy things now if you remember in
another video I did everything else we
install it's gonna go in the node
modules so if we want to add gzip for
animations that package is gonna be
installed and it's gonna lay in our node
modules so all the packages so rather
than linking things with the script tag
the packages locally in here and then
when we compile our code and it's ready
to be shipped it's gonna be included and
our final project okay so usually we'd
never almost never open this up we never
usually touch this this is kind of just
a folder that all the packages go in and
there are multiple packages
that we're gonna work with react then
we're gonna install through NPM and
they're all gonna be in here okay
so don't worry about this that's all I'm
trying to say public is gonna hold our
index.html and some to other files here
that don't really matter for now so we
just have an empty index.html here for
now okay that's all the public is and
most of our work is gonna be in this
source file so let me just skip through
this a bit we also have it get ignore
and what that does it basically if we're
trying to push up to github it's gonna
ignore these specific files that we have
in here so things like node modules this
can be huge if we download a lot of
packages and we don't necessarily want
to add this anywhere okay we don't want
to add it to github we don't want to add
it anywhere
so that's what get ignores it just
ignores all the files that we want to
push up
we have package that logs out JSON and
package that JSON and what this does it
just holds some scripts here in this
case we have his start script so what it
does it kind of just starts up our react
project if we have a final version and
we want to ship it so I have my react
project done we can run build and what
that's gonna do is it's gonna optimize
everything for us so it's very
compressed and it's ready to be put live
somewhere on a server okay we have tests
here which we're not gonna cover now and
what that's gonna do is we can run tests
to make sure that everything works the
way we want and eject which just kind of
shows you all the different packages
that we have installed in this project
but again don't really worry about this
for now we're just gonna close this up
and package that log that JSON basically
all it means is it's gonna hold a
specific version of each package that we
have included in here as you can see
it's kind of crazy here but what it does
basically is if we have if we give this
code some
else and they want to install it we are
sure that they have the same version as
us so in case one package gets updated
or something they still have our version
that we use on this PC so Wow ok this is
not even about react anymore but again
don't I wouldn't worry about these so
much and we have read me which just
gives us some basic this basic waste
that we can get started again we can
ignore this we don't care we don't care
and let's do react okay so let's open up
our source here and here is where we
write all of our code so the first thing
we have here is an app dot CSS it just
gives us some basic styling but let's
open up let's see actually what we get
here so we can go back to the terminal
and we can run NPM start and what that's
gonna do is just gonna open up a live
development server so we can see our
react code so it's gonna open up
obviously on the other screen so I have
to drag it in here and it's gonna take a
bit so let's just wait let's go back
here so all we have is some basic
styling in here we have something called
a BAS which we're gonna delete in a bit
because I don't want to overwhelm you
with all this code and we're gonna start
from scratch we have a test file which
again it doesn't really matter for this
one an index dot CSS which has all some
basic body styling and a code styling
here so let's take a look at what we got
okay so we just got this page here with
a logo and some some text okay and we
have an index J s here and what this
does it pretty much just mounts our
react app okay now this doesn't make any
sense so let me just delete everything
in here in here and our app is okay
because this is a component so I'm gonna
delete everything and then it's all
gonna make sense so we go back here
everything is breaking but that's fine
so what we need to
react the first thing is we need to
create a component now AB das is a
component now what a component basically
is is a file that holds all the logic
the HTML the logic and even styling in
one file so you can imagine a component
as being a self-contained piece of code
so may be a model is a good example you
can have a model that can be a component
and what you can have in there is the
HTML the JavaScript logic and is styling
so how can we create this component well
let's create this app component again
and we're going to render it to the
screen so the first thing we need to do
is always when create a component we
need to import react from react okay
that's the first thing we need to do and
how we can create a component is by
writing a function so we can just create
a function called app for this example
like so okay it's just normal function
perfect and now what it actually does
differently from like vanilla JavaScript
is we can return so we add return
parentheses like so and I'm just going
to write a div here and if that doesn't
work if you hit div and it doesn't work
and you hit tab we can go down here and
click this and we can write react here
and it's gonna recognize it as being a
react file so now we can create a Biff
here and I know this looks confusing as
hell but don't worry I'm gonna add h1
with hello react okay so this is one
component we have here I'm gonna explain
what everything happens in here in just
a second but don't worry and all I'm
gonna do now is just export default app
so what export default means is it's
just gonna export this file what happens
here is we create a component
we export it and then our index j s as
you can see here we have something
called import to react again we have
import react column and then in here we
use this react Dom render to render this
app component and then there's a comma
here and it says document dot get
element by ID oh wait that's just normal
JavaScript get document dot get element
by ID on this route all right edie now I
am super confused what's happening here
what's happening is that we rendered
this app component that we just created
in our index.html so as you can see we
get this route let's take a look at our
index.html in our public folder we're
gonna go here index.html as you can see
we don't have anything in our body here
basically react does is we don't have
any HTML everything gets generated
inside one div so our JavaScript takes
all of our components and it's gonna
generate from JavaScript all the HTML
rather than having HTML and then a
JavaScript separately and then you get
element by ID you get all all you select
everything separately you just have
JavaScript have everything in its tiles
HTML and everything and it generates it
inside this div for us okay and that's
what it does we import react we create
this function export it and it's gonna
be rendered in here so now if we take a
look here it's gonna say hello react so
we've successfully rendered this
function on the screen all right but
what's going on here because normally we
would not be able to use divs inside
functions well that's why we import to
react here what react gives the power to
us is that this does look like HTML here
but it's not HTML
what react does is if we return some
some code here so like a divin h1 this
is automatically gonna be compiled into
it's actually JavaScript because what
what this happens basically behind the
scenes it's something like this it's
gonna create it's gonna say react that
creates element and it's gonna create a
div for us so something like this this
is kind of what happens behind the
scenes here so this kind of means this
but react does that without without our
worry okay we don't have to worry about
these things so what we have now is we
can create these functions or components
I should say and then we can render them
out to the screen cool so we have this
div with a h1 of react okay so this is
our whole component again alright so
what else we can do well we can add
logic to this and the place we add the
logic is before when we return this HTML
again it's not a HTML it's something
called JSX
alright it's essentially just JavaScript
but if we want to add additional logic
we can do it up here so let's just
create a button here a a function that
says hello ok so we can create a Const
say hello I'm gonna just set it equal to
an arrow function alright and I'm gonna
console.log hello here
simple as that so now down here I can
just add a button that's gonna say hello
okay now rather than doing it like in
vanilla JavaScript where you would have
to go and get a reference to this button
like document the query selector and
then you would get the button that says
hello maybe so maybe you have a class of
hello on it and then you would do hello
dot the
eventlistener on click you don't need to
do these things anymore because what we
have here now is we have the function in
here and also the button so all we have
to do is we're gonna look at one event
listener on click that we can use and
all we have to do is go here on the
button and we can add an on click like
so on and then a Big C on click and we
can set this equal to something and as
you can see as you can notice here I'm
actually adding curly braces and what
curly braces means is that we can add
JavaScript in here so everything I write
in here is gonna be JavaScript okay if
we don't add this then it's just gonna
be plain HTML okay so this would be HTML
if we add a bracket then it's gonna
curly brace then it's gonna be
JavaScript so in here look I'm also
going to create a Const counter it's
gonna set it equal to zero and in here
rather than saying hello I can add 0
that's gonna work fine as you can see
it's a zero there but I can even add
this JavaScript number just by adding
these curly braces and saying counter
hit save and as you can see I still have
0 so that's what we can do here I'm
gonna change this back to hello I'm
an on click here and I'm gonna set it
equal to say hello so I'm gonna run this
function say hello like so hit save I'm
not gonna add parenthesis here because
that would invoke the function as soon
as it gets rendered on the screen so I
just have a reference to it and now if
we take a look and hit f12 we're gonna
see that every time we click hello it's
gonna console.log and it's gonna execute
this function so look at that we have
everything self-contained look how much
faster and cleaner this looks super cool
all right what else can we do well we
can create other Campo
as well so maybe I don't want this to be
in my app maybe I want to have this
hello components a like a specific code
that does something in another file well
we can do that we can go in our source
here I'm going to create a new file I'm
gonna say say hello dot J yes all right
this is gonna be a new file now we can
create another component I can create an
I can say import react again we're gonna
do this every time from react so we're
just gonna import the react package
again from our node modules alright and
then we can create a function say a
let's create a function hello
okay so this is gonna be our Hello
component and then here again we can
just return he div and we're gonna have
to switch this through react again a div
that has a button of say hello and we
can add the logic from here to here
there we go it's save alright so we have
this component now now we can get rid of
everything from here so I'm just gonna
have some empty dibs
okay we're gonna go back here again so
we have to say hello I'm just gonna add
and I'll click again so that's equal to
add the curly braces say hello perfect
so now we can export this Hello
component export default hello default I
cannot write any more hello all right
let's save go back here and now rather
than doing all the logic here we can
just import hello from and we can
navigate to our say hello component and
now look at the cool thing we can do all
we have to do to render this component
here is we can just write it like a HTML
so we can do hello like so look at that
that's that's kind of weird isn't it but
it's safe and what we get is we still
get that component showing up on the
screen so again we can have here
is the app component alright this is the
app component and in here in our say
hello I can add something else let's add
a hate stream this is the hello
component with its own logic and
everything hit save and as you can see
it still renders on the screen so we can
kind of modularize all of our code into
these separate small files and then we
can just render them in here so that's
super super cool all right let's take a
look everything still works
press hello hello hello everything works
alright but this is a very unrealistic
kind of component so let's get rid of it
I'm gonna hit delete and let's get rid
of this to you so I'm kind of kind of
similar let's remove this import because
we don't have that anymore
I'm gonna say hello react here again hit
save and what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna
add create a component that kind of
looks like a tweet something that we
would have on Twitter so let's create a
new file I'm gonna say tweet dot J s
react from react and I just create a
function called tweet and I'm gonna kind
of think of how my tweet is gonna look
I'm gonna return parenthesis and I'm
gonna have a div here oh my god let me
switch to react again I'm gonna have a
div here and what do I want in my tweet
well I want a message maybe so I'm gonna
add a let's say we have a name so
someone that weeds I'm gonna add the h3
of name I'm gonna have the tweet message
that's a day Pete for that this is a
random tweet that wet
he wrote web anyway and let's say we
want to also have the number of likes to
show up on the screen so for that I'm
just gonna add another let's add another
h3 number of likes all right let's save
and now we can import this again import
tweet from
dot slash tweet now all we have to do
again is down here I'm gonna render this
component hit save and we don't doesn't
work because it says attempted import
does not contain a default export so we
have to go back here and our tweet and
say export default tweet you're gonna
see that we have this name this random
tweet and the number of likes showing up
on the screen perfect and now we can
also style this so how can we style
different things well we can go down to
our ab dot CSS here and we can create a
tweet class for example maybe I want a a
border of five of two pixels solid black
to this okay it's safe and now to add an
actual class to our tweet let's go back
to our tweet component here we cannot
use class we need to use class name and
react and the reason we need to add
class name is because we are in
JavaScript again you always have to
remember that everything we do in here
is essentially JavaScript and class
means a constructor function structure
function in JavaScript so that's not
gonna work okay so we need to make sure
we do class name but something that
react came up with two to let us know
that this is how we can add different
styles so if we take a look nothing
happens because we need to import our
styles as well so we can say import dot
slash and we can say app dot CSS like so
let's save and now as you can see we
have the border on top of this now to
make this a bit nicer I guess we can go
back to AB dot CSS we can kind of delete
all of this code here and we can get the
app we can just create an app and add a
height of 100 VH to this a background of
light blue maybe hit save actually I'm
going to change this color a bit
something like that and then we can go
back to our app and add a class name
here
of app-like so I believe I did lowercase
so hit app and as you can see everything
is good let's also get rid of those
margins and everything I'm gonna just do
it in this index dot CSS up here I'm
gonna add a star sign and margin:0
padding:0 and box sizing border box to
get rid of everything there we go and
now I'm just gonna make this white okay
so we can go back to the F dot CSS so we
have our tweet here I'm gonna add a
default height of like 300 pixels to it
and a width of 300 pixels okay let's get
that box kind of look to it perfect so
let's add a background of white alright
and we can actually get rid of this
border I don't like the way this border
looks I'm gonna add a border radius of
30 pixels alright it's something like
that that doesn't look that great we can
also add a display flex flex Direction
column justify content center actually
let's do space round and on line items
Center hit save and this is what we have
we have the name random tweet and the
number of likes very very cool all right
components well look at this we can just
go back to our app dot j s here and if I
want multiple instances of this tweet I
can just copy and paste this multiple
times now look at that that's gonna
create as multiple components of this
tweet alright but we still have name
here and this is some random tweet and
number of lights here everything is
still static it doesn't look good
all right so how can we make this a bit
more interesting well for now let me
just add a min height here so it extends
all right that way if we have more
content here it doesn't cut off that
blue perfect I'm also gonna add a
display flex to this
just kind of put them like that that's
ugly okay let's do it justify content
space around alright there we go so
something like that that looks a bit it
still looks bad a line items in there
all right I'm gonna actually get rid of
this hello because it doesn't have any
meaning to us anymore
hit save alright so there we go we have
four lovely tweets going on here okay
now how can we add custom names to it
well we can define a prop and what a
prop is is a property that we can define
on each individual component so here if
I want maybe I can add a name I'm gonna
set a name equal to and I can just add a
name David alright there we go I can add
for each individual ones just copy and
paste everything so for this one
I can add something different let's say
I want to add John Snow
Game of Thrones is coming so we have to
prepare winter is coming
that's a name that's alleged name I'm
not even joking delete this and let's
also add mosh mosh there we go hit save
and you know what let's add Travis
e-media
there we go head saved perfect so
in our tweets da yes we still have name
rendering here so if we add name in here
the props what we have available in here
is this name prop so in our tweet in the
parameters here on the component we can
add a prop a props I apologize a props
parameter okay and now we can access the
name by writing prompts dot name hit
save and make sure if we take a look now
it says props that name
so it's this random text please remember
if you wanna
use JavaScript in this JSX in this HTML
code we need to add these curly braces
so now if we add props thought name hit
save now you're gonna see David John
snow traversing media and mosh so how
cool is that now what we can also do is
we can add the number of likes the
number of tweets and everything else in
here so maybe I want to have the tweet
here so I can say message set equal to
paste this for now paste it in here in
here and in here and I can just change
this what does John snow say I am the
true king and then tree of terror see
media just hit 700k my dudes that's what
he's gonna say him Maj is my new course
is available there we go hit save and
now again to render this we still don't
have anything all we have to do is go
back to tweet and rather than rendering
this plain message we can just add curly
braces and we can say props dot and
whatever we have here so the prop name
is message we can copy this and paste it
in here props that message hits save
let's take a look and as you can see
this is random tweet I am the true king
700k my dudes and my new course is
available so you can do the same thing
with the likes as well if you want so
that's a good practice and give it a
shot there we go
that is those are props and if you want
you don't even need to write props dot
name prompt stop message in here rather
than writing props you can add curly
braces and kind of Deconstructor this
with name and with message so you can
kind of extract the name end message so
rather than writing prompts that name
you can just have name and you can just
have my
all right this is a bit of es6 which
we're gonna use a ton and our react it's
safe and this should work
yeah the same way so everything is still
good everything is perfect we got it
goin
now one last important thing I want to
cover in this video is something called
state and a state again if you look over
the internet and trying to figure out
what it is it can be quite complicated
and everybody's just trying to make it
look like super complicated but it's not
that complicated
so what state basically is is some data
so you can imagine it as a variable and
based on that data your app kind of
renders itself based on that data so
maybe you have a a is logged in a
boolean that can be false and true and
based on that state your app changes so
if and maybe is logged in is true then
maybe your HTML might look differently
so besides stop talking and let's start
showing I'm gonna delete this tweet
everything in here in this tweet and I'm
gonna get back to the it later and what
we can do we can create a state like so
we can say Const so it's kind of like a
variable and actually before we add the
cons we need to go up here and we need
to import one specific thing from react
we're gonna add a comma and we're gonna
add some curly braces and we're gonna
say use state okay you stayed like so
and in here now what we can do is we can
say use state and in here and this
parameter we can add the data that we
want either that can be a boolean a
false true value in number string
whatever you want okay so how can we
adil and what what should we add well
let's say we want to create a a a text
and when we click on it it's gonna
change its color or something like that
so let's add a false for now okay and in
here we can create a Const
and then what we need to do is we need
to add these curly brackets and we need
to set it equal to you state and the
first thing that we need to do is we
need to give it a name
so in this case we're gonna add a is red
alright we're gonna add a comma to it
and the second thing that we need to do
is we need to add a name that can change
this value so first one is the actual
name and the second thing will be kind
of a function that changes that is read
value so we can switch it from true to
false so you're gonna see this it's very
common we're gonna use something called
set okay set read that's how I'm gonna
call it and maybe if we have a count I'm
gonna create a count
- we're gonna create a count and then
we're gonna add a comma we're gonna say
step count all right I'm gonna say set
it equal to you state and we're gonna
start the count from zero all right so
let's experiment with these two and here
this kind of switch so let me go back
let's just create let's try it with the
count first because that might be
simpler all right I'm gonna have a
button here and I'm gonna say increment
perfect and then I'm just gonna have a
h1 and rather than putting zero here I'm
gonna put that count from this state
okay
hits save let's take a look so we have
increment and we have a zero there
perfect so how can we increment this
well we can create a function we can see
Const increment we're gonna set this
equal to an arrow function and the way
we need to work with state is we use
this set count so set count I'm gonna
add this is a function and in here what
I want to do is I want count plus 1 and
that's it and here on the button I can
add an on click set this equal to our
function increment
hit save and now as you can see when we
click it automatically is going to
re-render this number and it's going to
increment for us so again based on our
state our HTML is gonna change whatever
you have in your state your HTML is
changing so rather than adding fixed
values in here we just create and we
just add our state in here alright so if
we're gonna eventually we're gonna get
some data from an API and we would save
that in a state so you would have
something like this cost user and then
set user or something like that and you
would have this equal to used State and
you would have an object here with all
the different things that the user has
maybe it has a name of add maybe it has
an age of 25 maybe I have posts here and
then it's gonna be an array of objects
or just an array maybe I have a my first
post my lovely summer it's not even
summer yet anyway so this is what you
would have and then you would render
everything out here and then you would
just change the state if you want to add
another post or something like that and
then everything is kind of automatically
magically gonna render itself based on
whatever you have in here okay so that's
what these state is so as you can see
now we have this for a king let's also
add a h1 here and we're gonna try with
the the other one here and I'm gonna
show you how we can actually switch
classes change my color like so it's
save you're gonna see we have a change
my color here and now rather you know
what I can do is I can go into my index
that's have that CSS in here and I can
just create a red class for example and
I can just change the color to red and
add a font size of 50 pixels head Save
we
I go back to our ideas here and what we
can do is we can set a class name on
this h1 now here's the cool part we can
set it equal to I'm gonna add curly
braces and what I'm gonna do is I'm
gonna check this is red if it's true or
false and based on that we can add the
class name or remove it so what we can
do in here is we can add a ternary
operator now we can check that is red
value so we can write is red and if this
is true we can add a question mark this
is true then I 1p class red to be added
and then you can add these the colon
here else this would mean else so this
is like an if-else statement else
I don't want to add anything to it hit
save all right so now let's take a look
when we click this count button I want
to change the value to red as well so we
can say well we're not gonna use the set
count we're gonna set the red now so
we're gonna say set red to true hit save
and I'll take a look let's go back here
once we click increment look at that we
added the class if I want this to to
toggle we can add a is red and then I
can just switch its value from true to
false by adding an exclamation mark and
that's gonna say hey the opposite of
whatever the value is right now so if
this is false it's gonna become true
when we played it again it's gonna be
the opposite of true when we click again
it's going to be the opposite of false
it's save and now as you can see it's
gonna toggle let's take a look now we
are toggling it so that's a way that we
can also add and remove classes and
react so as you can see it's quite
different from vanilla JavaScript but
it's it's way more logical and it's way
more cleaner and quickly to finish this
off with the basics I'm gonna show you a
good example that we could use the sweet
and a real world world project so while
we would have
is we would have an API call and we
would get all the tweets in here and we
would set it in this you state for now
we're not gonna make an API call or
we're gonna get a user we're gonna add a
set user for now we're gonna set this
equal to you state and here we're gonna
have an object and what we're gonna have
in this object is basically a name and a
title or a description name and see
well actually we are gonna have to have
an array of objects because we want to
have multiple objects so I'm gonna set
in the array and here I'm gonna have a
name of head and a message of hello
there then we're gonna create another
object name we're gonna see John again
with the message of I am John Snow and
let's create another one we're gonna
have a name of Travis E and a message of
I am awesome so you can imagine that we
would get this from an API and then we
would set it in this state so now here
I'm gonna delete everything and in this
app this is what I'm gonna do I'm gonna
add curly braces I'm gonna get the user
dot map I'm gonna map over this and I'm
gonna get the info so all the
information from this rate of users and
actually a better way we could name this
as users here set users and then we
would have users dot map and we would
get each user in here I'm just gonna run
an arrow function I'm not gonna add the
curly braces here so I'm gonna leave it
empty here I'm gonna add a parenthesis
because I want to return some HTML
well JSX because we learned that this is
actually JavaScript and then here what
I'm gonna return is actually this tweet
like so nice hit save and now we're
gonna get three tweets one two entry but
we didn't render anything inside here so
what we can do
is we can add the name and the messages
from here and the prompts we can say
name is gonna be equal to curly braces
and we can get all the information from
the state and that is user dot name okay
so users and the name here perfect and
we can add the message I believe it's
set as message yeah we can get the
message to be equal to user dot message
and now everything just works magically
look at that that's how we can use the
state together with components to create
some very very cool things so that's it
that's react I didn't cover anything I
know because I didn't want to overwhelm
you with a lot of crazy things we still
have a lot of things to cover such as
fetching an eighth from an API use
effect and router and state management
ah there's so much more it's crazy but
let me know if you want to see more
leave it down in the comments and that's
it from me I want to see your reaction
to this video and I'll see you next time
but the big balloon
[Music]